We spoke with an undercover FBI agent.
>> My name is Scott Payne. I infiltrated
biker gangs, the KKK, and America's
neo-Nazis.
>> Here are three incredible takeaways
about going undercover that you won't
hear anywhere else. Creating an
undercover identity is more than just
getting a new name. It's a process of
creating a believable backstory that
avoids suspicion. Listen to Scott
explain his technique.
>> For me personally, the way I was trained
[music] and the choices I made always
stuck close to very close to who I am.
I'm going to still me. The jokes are the
same. I just may or may not be married
and may or may not have kids. But I mean
I
probably ride motorcycles and lift
weights.
>> Agents are told to avoid using drugs
while undercover, even if a target ask
them to, with one important exception.
>> You don't do dope.
Now, if your life's in danger, yeah,
I'll do the dope.
And then I need to tell the case team.
And I need to tell the United States
Attorney's Office, and I need to get to
an emergency room and let them know that
I've ingested a drug to make sure I'm
not going to OD.
>> Undercover training at the FBI Academy
is designed to be grueling with
psychological testing, role-playing
scenarios, and sleep deprivation. As an
instructor for almost two decades, Scott
says the pressure is intentional.
>> I've never seen a 100% graduation rate.
That doesn't mean it's hazing. I mean,
that that to [music] me it gives the
course credibility. You go through that
process and if you make it, it's [music]
2 weeks, no days off.
Pretty big on sleep deprivation cuz it
really brings out the weaknesses. And we
want to see that as trainers, as
undercovers. We want you to feel it.
>> If you like this, then watch the full
interview on Insider's YouTube channel
and follow for more.